{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This city’s boundaries, which are marked by stones placed a mile apart, were surveyed by a team including African-American Benjamin Banneker who was born in a county bordering this city. Andrew Ellicott revised the initial design for this city created by Pierre Charles L’Enfant. Legend has it that Dolley Madison rescued a portrait of this city’s namesake from an executive mansion before it was burned in the War of 1812. The White House can be found in, for ten points, what capital of the United States?",
      "answer": [
        "Washington, DC or District of Columbia,",
        "either Washington",
        "DC"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man successfully saved his force by linking with Metellus at the River Muthul. Cimbri king Boiorix was soundly defeated by this general and Catulus in Cisalpine Gaul at the Battle of Vercellae. This politician named “Reforms” which lifted property requirements for legion service and instituted that soldiers carry all their supplies and weapons, making a baggage train unnecessary. For ten points, name this Roman who was elected to the consulship seven times, sometimes known as the “Third Founder of Rome.”",
      "answer": "Gaius Marius"
    },
    {
      "question": "Only this island and the Faeroe Islands were in the band of totality of the total solar eclipse on March 20th, 2015. This island has no visa requirement and is officially designated a demilitarized zone by the Kingdom of Norway. Due to a lack of tectonic activity and extensive permafrost, the Norwegian government selected this island’s administrative center of Longyearbyen to host its Global Seed Vault. For ten points, name this Arctic island formerly known as Spitsbergen.",
      "answer": [
        "Svalbard",
        "Spitsbergen before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A \"monastery\" in this city contains inscriptions that refer to the cult of king Obodas I, who opposed the Hasmoneans. Johann Ludwig Burckhardt visited this city in 1812, believing it housed Aaron's Tomb. Local Bedouins supposedly tried to earn riches by shooting urns in this city's al-Khazneh, or Treasury, which is believed to be the mausoleum of Aretas IV. People entered this capital of the Nabateans through its narrow Siq entrance. For ten points, name this ancient rock-cut city in Jordan.",
      "answer": "Petra 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Finals"
    },
    {
      "question": "The daughter of Doris and Nereus, this goddess’s Roman equivalent was Salacia. In a 17th century tapestry, this goddess is depicted giving the ring of King Minos to the hero Theseus, her husband’s son. A ceremonial pool on the grounds of the US Merchant Marine Academy is named after this goddess, and an 1866 statue in the Louvre by Francois Theodore Devaulx [[deh-VOH]] depicts this goddess carrying a downturned trident. For ten points, name this Greek goddess of the sea and wife of Poseidon.",
      "answer": "Amphitrite ]"
    },
    {
      "question": "This general was sent to Illinois to lead in the Black Hawk War, arriving just in time to negotiate the war’s end. This man oversaw the process of Indian Removal from Florida, and though he never graduated from West Point, this man holds the distinction of being the longest-serving general in American history. During the Civil War, this man developed the Union strategy known as the Anaconda Plan. For ten points, name this American general who defeated Santa Anna and captured Mexico City in 1847.",
      "answer": "Winfield Scott"
    },
    {
      "question": "This thinker's mother supposedly took a pair of scissors and cut the cloth she had been weaving after his absence from school. This man used the example of a child falling down a well to explain innate goodness using the metaphor of the four beginnings. This thinker likely studied with the author of The Doctrine of the Mean, Zisi. This thinker recorded his conversations with various rulers in the last of the Four Books. For ten points, name this \"second sage\" who followed Confucius's ideologies.",
      "answer": "Mencius or Mengzi"
    },
    {
      "question": "This author of My Larger Education and The Man Farthest Down received support from Andrew Carnegie when he established the National Negro Business League in 1900. This leader faced a backlash after giving the Atlanta Compromise speech in support of white political rule. Author of the autobiography, Up From Slavery, this man was the first African- American to be depicted on a United States postage stamp. For ten points, name this first president of the Tuskegee Institute.",
      "answer": "Booker T. Washington"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man created The Prayer two months after leaving the workshop of Auguste Rodin. This artist’s rendering of Princess Marie Bonaparte was deemed “scandalous and vulgar” by the Salon des Indépendants. That work is now on display in Philadelphia, as is this man’s best known sculpture, which served as the inspiration for the Clio Awards statuette. For ten points, name this creator of the bronze castings known as Sleeping Muse, a Romanian master best known for the Bird in Space series.",
      "answer": [
        "Constantin Brancusi ]",
        "close pronunciations, including any that include a third, vowel syllable 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Finals"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man succeeded Friedrich Ebert [[EE-buht]] as president of the Weimar [[VYE- mar]] Republic. Although he had won a spectacular victory at the Battle of Tannenberg, this man promulgated the “stab-in-the-back” theory regarding Germany’s defeat in World War One. In 1933, after years of resisting Hitler’s rise, this man felt he had no option but to appoint him as chancellor. For ten points, name this last pre-World War Two president of Germany, whose name christened an ill-fated airship.",
      "answer": "Paul von Hindenburg 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Finals"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person's students included Mary Putnam Jacobi, and she founded a school with Sophia Jex-Blake. Elizabeth Garret Anderson was mentored by this person who founded a dispensary at Tompkins Square while working with Marie Zakrzewska. This person adopted Kitty Barry, on whom she tested theories of Physical Education. This woman was allowed to attend Geneva College, where she wrote a thesis on typhoid fever. For ten points, name this woman, the first to receive a medical degree in the United States.",
        "answer": "Elizabeth Blackwell"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1861, Blackwell was beaten out for the role of Superintendent of Army Nurses by this woman who made her name as an advocate for the mentally ill.",
        "answer": "Dorothea Dix"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man negotiated a deal with Marcellus to defeat Bogud and began his public career as triumvir monetalis, the overseer of the mint. Gaius Maecenas spoiled a plot by this man's wife, Junia Secunda, in which Lucius Saenius Balbinus gave bail. After trying to quash the Sicilian revolt, this man was removed from power. This Master of the Horse for Julius Caesar was the last Pontifex Maximus prior to the Roman Empire. For ten points, name this man who joined Mark Antony and Octavian to form the Second Triumvirate.",
        "answer": "Marcus Aemilius Lepidus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Lepidus lost much of his territory to Octavian after this 42 BC battle, the final battle of the Wars of the Second Triumvirate, which took place at the same Macedonian city where Saint Paul first preached in Europe.",
        "answer": "Battle of Philippi"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country's ruling party fractured in 2015 with Amama Mbabazi forming the GO FORWARD group. The National Resistance Movement has been in power in this country since 1986. This country's military arrested politician Bobi Wine days after he announced his nomination for president in 2021. In January, 2021, Yoweri Museveni was reelected to a 6th term to govern this country. Milton Obote was removed from power in this country by a man who faced the Entebbe Raid. For ten points, name this African country that was led by Idi Amin.",
        "answer": "Republic of Uganda"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Museveni has faced a 34 year insurgency by this guerilla group. Its leader, Joseph Kony, believes he is inhabited by a Chinese phantom and has abducted children to be soldiers.",
        "answer": [
          "Lord's Resistance Army",
          "LRA 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Finals"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A party in this state included \"Dragons of Death\" and FICO groups and that party uses \"zebra lists\" in which every third person must be a woman. Eduardo Montane, a history professor at Syracuse University, led a party in this country that Samora Machel would soon govern. Joaquim Chissano helped this country sign the Lusaka Accord. FRELIMO brought independence to this country from Portugal. For ten points, name this country with capital at Maputo, which names a strait that separates it and Madagascar.",
        "answer": "Republic of Mozambique"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mozambique came under the control of Portugal in the years following this explorer's 1498 voyage around the Cape of Good Hope.",
        "answer": "Vasco da Gama"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man explained how different groups could unite to create basic social constructs with the term “overlapping consensus.” This man wrote an essay that is subtitled \"Political not Metaphysical\" which focuses on the principles of liberty and equality. One of this man's works includes the idea of improving the position of the worst off, known as the “difference principle.” This man created a thought experiment based on the “veil of ignorance.” For ten points, name this philosopher who wrote A Theory of Justice.",
        "answer": "John Rawls"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This philosopher responded to Rawls with his libertarian work, Anarchy, State and Utopia. He created the idea of evolutionary cosmology in Invariances.",
        "answer": "Robert Nozick"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Elmer Thomas added a \"third horse\" to this law that created an \"honest dollar\" by controlling the amount of silver. This law was amended in 1935 by allowing for school lunches in Section 32. This law enforced the 1929 Potato Control Law and was found to be unconstitutional in 1936’s United States v. Butler. Pregnant sows were sold and oranges were destroyed according to this law. For ten points, name this New Deal law meant to boost prices and lower surpluses.",
        "answer": "Agricultural Adjustment Act"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Justice Owen Roberts wrote the majority opinion in US v. Butler and was joined in that opinion by this Chief Justice, a former governor of New York, and the Republican presidential nominee in 1916.",
        "answer": "Charles Evans Hughes 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Finals"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This river is the site of the Gariep Dam, which has been used for irrigation by the local Khoekhoe [[KO-KO]] people. This river enters the ocean near Alexander Bay and descends at Augrabies [[aw-GRAH-beez]] Falls. This river was named by Robert Gordon, who introduced Merino sheep to the Cape Colony. This river passes through only one city, Upington, and flows on the border of Lesotho [[luh-SOO-too]] and Namibia from the Drakensberg Mountains. For ten points, name this longest river within South Africa, named for the Dutch ruling family.",
        "answer": [
          "Orange River",
          "Gariep River, Groote River,",
          "Senqu River"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Orange River flows south of this South African city, the capital of Northern Cape Province. This city, which contains a notable \"Big Hole,\" was where the De Beers family established its diamond company.",
        "answer": "Kimberley, South Africa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this man’s rule, sociology was barred as a discipline, and his wife was awarded a PhD in chemistry despite a lack of scientific competence and cheating. In the 1980s, this man's “shock therapy” austerity policy caused power cuts that resulted in the loss of many lives. This man created the July Theses as part of \"Socialist Realism,” and miners in the Jiu Valley struck against this man over pay. This man succeeded Gheorghe Gheorghiu-Dej and created the Securitate [[seh-kur-eh-TAH-tay]] secret police. For ten points, name this president, overthrown in the 1989 Romanian revolution.",
        "answer": "Nicolae Ceausescu ]"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 1989 Romanian Revolution began with demonstrations in this third-largest city in Romania, located on the Bega River, the cultural center of Western Romania.",
        "answer": "Timisoara ]"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Over the course of Abercrombie & Fitch's history, name the......",
      "prompt": "Name the over the course of abercrombie & fitch's history, name the.........",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Densely populated core borough of New York City in which it first started.",
          "answer": "Manhattan"
        },
        {
          "question": "American aviator whom they outfitted for his flight on the Spirit of St. Louis.",
          "answer": "Charles Lindbergh"
        },
        {
          "question": "NYC Avenue on which the store was located, today identified with the advertising industry.",
          "answer": "Madison Avenue"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sales method pioneered by Sears that they used to expand their market beyond stores.",
          "answer": [
            "Mail order",
            "Catalogue,",
            "descriptive answers indicating receiving deliveries by mail"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Chinese rummy-like tile game it introduced to US audiences.",
          "answer": "Mahjong"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northern Mariana Island where they were accused of having sweatshops.",
          "answer": "Saipan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Star of Man’s Favorite Sport, one of the first product placement films, nominated for an Oscar for Giant.",
          "answer": "Rock Hudson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Oldest department store in the US which William Humphreys headed before coming to Abercrombie & Fitch.",
          "answer": "Lord & Taylor 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Finals"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Portuguese-English Relations",
      "prompt": "Name the…...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital of Portugal, a vital Red Cross base for the Allies in World War Two.",
          "answer": "Lisbon"
        },
        {
          "question": "City once known as Bombay, given as a dowry to England by Portugal.",
          "answer": "Mumbai"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty between John I and Philippa of Lancaster, sharing its name with the House of Queen Elizabeth II.",
          "answer": "Windsor"
        },
        {
          "question": "War in which Portugal allied with England after the Battle of Blenheim.",
          "answer": "War of the Spanish Succession"
        },
        {
          "question": "Portuguese Dynasty of Charles II's wife, founded by John I.",
          "answer": "Braganza"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty that guaranteed both nations would not tax wines and textiles.",
          "answer": "Methuen Treaty"
        },
        {
          "question": "War England helped to bring back Portuguese self-rule from Spain.",
          "answer": [
            "Restoration War",
            "Acclamation War"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Map of Portugal's African claims that forced the 1890 British Ultimatum.",
          "answer": "Rose-coloured Map or Pink Map 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Finals"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Janissary Corps",
      "prompt": "Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Gunpowder empire which utilized the Janissary corps",
          "answer": "Ottoman Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital of the Byzantine Empire captured by Janissaries led by Mehmed the Conqueror.",
          "answer": [
            "Constantinople",
            "Istanbul",
            "Konstantiniyye"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Facial feature the Janissaries were banned from growing, unlike most Muslims.",
          "answer": "Beards"
        },
        {
          "question": "1526 battle where a timely Janissary charge crushed the forces of Louis II of Hungary.",
          "answer": "Battle of Mohacs"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ottoman system of taxing conquered people to benefit low-level bureaucrats and Janissary soldiers.",
          "answer": "Devshirme"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Incident” that led to the dissolution of the Janissary corps in the 19th century.",
          "answer": "Auspicious Incident"
        },
        {
          "question": "Janissary who served as de facto leader of the Ottoman Empire after the death of Suleiman the Magnificent.",
          "answer": "Sokollu Mehmed Pasha"
        },
        {
          "question": "19th century Sultan, deposed by the Janissary elite; another sultan with this name was known as \"The Mean.\"",
          "answer": "Selim III 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Finals"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1970, this man distributed fake campaign flyers at a rock concert to disrupt the election of Alan Dixon. This man was opposed by Robert Edgeworth and Terry Dolan to head the College Republicans. This man used “push (20 pts)",
        "polling” to insinuate that a candidate's staff was \"dominated by lesbians\" to help his client beat Ann Richards. This man helped elect men like John Ashcroft, Bill Clements, and John (10 pts)",
        "Cornyn. Nicknamed the \"Architect,” for ten points, name this Chief Strategist and Chief of Staff for George W. Bush."
      ],
      "answer": "Karl Rove"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this country, national hero Keppetipola Disawe [[dih-SAH-weh]] launched the Uva Rebellion of 1818 against Governor Robert Brownrigg. A conflict in this country was fought between the government and a group that wanted to establish an ethnic homeland called (20 pts)",
        "Eelam, the latter of which assassinated Indian Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi. The Dutch gained control of this country's coastal areas during its (10 pts)",
        "Kingdom of Kandy. For ten points, name this island country that faced a civil war between a Sinhalese government and the Tamil Tigers."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Democratic Socialist Republic of Sri Lanka",
        "Ceylon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This conscientious objector and trumpeter shot himself in the foot after being enlisted into the Royal Military Band in World War Two. As a composer, this man wrote Concerto for Two Pianos, one of the most often-played works for (*) three hands. From 1947 to 1970, this man wrote the scores for more than 100 films, including Whistle Down the Wind, The Inn of the Sixth Happiness, and (*) Hobson’s Choice. For ten points, name this man who won an Academy Award for the music to David Lean’s The Bridge on the River Kwai."
      ],
      "answer": "Malcolm Arnold"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this country, people including Jeremiah Chitunda were killed in the Halloween Massacre, which occurred in response to the Bicesse Accords. The Ovimbundu cities of Kuito and Huambo in this country were destroyed during a conflict which included the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Cuito Cuanavale. During this country's civil war, Holden Roberto’s FNLA and Jonas Savimbi’s UNITA fought against Agostinho Neto’s (10 pts)",
        "MPLA. This African country was the primary source of slaves for Brazilian plantations. For ten points, name this former Portuguese colony governed from Luanda."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Angola 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Finals"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This character’s origins can be traced as far back as Molière’s Don Juan, or The Stone Guest. Jean-Honoré Fragonard depicted this character as a boy forcing a taciturn smile. In Antoine Watteau’s painting of this character, dressed in his traditional (20 pts)",
        "baggy white clothes, he was given the name “Gilles.” This character loses his love interest Columbine to Harlequin, resulting in his perpetual (10 pts)",
        "disconsolate demeanor. For ten points, name this staple character of commedia dell'arte, the embodiment of the sad clown."
      ],
      "answer": "Pierrot ]"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A preacher with this surname criticized striking railroad workers, saying that \"the man who cannot live on bread and water is not fit to live,\" causing cries at labor rallies of “Hang (this surname).” That man with this surname raised money to buy (20 pts)",
        "rifles during the Bleeding Kansas crisis that came to be known as his namesake \"Bibles.” Abraham Lincoln said that an author with this (10 pts)",
        "maiden name, “Wrote the book that started this great war.\" For ten points, what surname was shared by preacher Henry Ward and his sister, the author of Uncle Tom's Cabin, Harriet Stowe?"
      ],
      "answer": "Beecher"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2013, this island became its own governorate after detaching from the Hadhramaut [[hah-drah-MAWT]] Governorate over 250 miles away. A local legend claims that Thomas the Apostle shipwrecked on this island in 52 CE on his way to evangelize (20 pts)",
        "India. This island is home to nearly 700 unique, endemic species, leading some to call it “the most alien-looking place on earth.” This island, which constitutes approximately 95% of the landmass of its namesake archipelago, is closer to (10 pts)",
        "Somalia than the country to which it belongs. For ten points, name this Yemeni island located in the Arabian Sea."
      ],
      "answer": "Socotra"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man's lover is shown in the Mondragone marble statue and was celebrated by Karl Heinrich Ulrichs using the pen name \"Numa Numantius\". Pnacrates wrote a poem about this man's heroism, about which a tondo was later placed on Arch of (20 pts)",
        "Constantine. This man's lover was with him when he killed the Marousian lion and was the Bithynian Greek Antinous. This man rebuilt the Serapeum of Alexandria and the (10 pts)",
        "Pantheon. In Judaea, this man ended the Bar Kokhba revolt. For ten points, name this successor of Trajan."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Hadrian",
        "Caesar Traianus Hadrianus 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Finals"
      ]
    }
  ]
}